<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' standalone='no'?>
<doxygen xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="compound.xsd" version="1.9.3" xml:lang="en-US">
  <compounddef id="md__d___ray_tracing_docs__r_e_a_d_m_e_os2" kind="page">
    <compoundname>md_D__RayTracing_docs_README_os2</compoundname>
    <title>Simple DirectMedia Layer 2 for OS/2 &amp; eComStation</title>
    <briefdescription>
    </briefdescription>
    <detaileddescription>
<para>SDL port for OS/2, authored by Andrey Vasilkin <ulink url="mailto:digi@os2.snc.ru">digi@os2.snc.ru</ulink>, 2016</para>
<para>OpenGL and audio capture not supported by this port.</para>
<para>Additional optional environment variables:</para>
<para>SDL_AUDIO_SHARE Values: 0 or 1, default is 0 Initializes the device as shareable or exclusively acquired.</para>
<para>SDL_VIDEODRIVER Values: DIVE or VMAN, default is DIVE Use video subsystem: Direct interface video extensions (DIVE) or Video Manager (VMAN).</para>
<para>You may significantly increase video output speed with OS4 kernel and patched files vman.dll and dive.dll or with latest versions of ACPI support and video driver Panorama.</para>
<para>Latest versions of OS/4 kernel: <ulink url="http://gus.biysk.ru/os4/">http://gus.biysk.ru/os4/</ulink> (Info: <ulink url="https://www.os2world.com/wiki/index.php/Phoenix_OS/4">https://www.os2world.com/wiki/index.php/Phoenix_OS/4</ulink>)</para>
<para>Patched files vman.dll and dive.dll: <ulink url="http://gus.biysk.ru/os4/test/pached_dll/PATCHED_DLL.RAR">http://gus.biysk.ru/os4/test/pached_dll/PATCHED_DLL.RAR</ulink></para>
<sect1 id="md__d___ray_tracing_docs__r_e_a_d_m_e_os2_1autotoc_md85">
<title>Compiling:</title>
<para>Open Watcom 1.9 or newer is tested. For the new Open Watcom V2 fork, see: <ulink url="https://github.com/open-watcom/">https://github.com/open-watcom/</ulink> and <ulink url="https://open-watcom.github.io">https://open-watcom.github.io</ulink> WATCOM environment variable must to be set to the Open Watcom install directory. To compile, run: wmake -f Makefile.os2</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="md__d___ray_tracing_docs__r_e_a_d_m_e_os2_1autotoc_md86">
<title>Installing:</title>
<para><itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>eComStation:</para>
<para>If you have previously installed SDL2, make a Backup copy of SDL2.dll located in D:\ecs\dll (where D: is disk on which installed eComStation). Stop all programs running with SDL2. Copy SDL2.dll to D:\ecs\dll</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>OS/2:</para>
<para>Copy SDL2.dll to any directory on your LIBPATH. If you have a previous version installed, close all SDL2 applications before replacing the old copy. Also make sure that any other older versions of DLLs are removed from your system.</para>
</listitem></itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="md__d___ray_tracing_docs__r_e_a_d_m_e_os2_1autotoc_md87">
<title>Joysticks in SDL2:</title>
<para>The joystick code in SDL2 is a direct forward-port from the SDL-1.2 version. Here is the original documentation from SDL-1.2:</para>
<para>The Joystick detection only works for standard joysticks (2 buttons, 2 axes and the like). Therefore, if you use a non-standard joystick, you should specify its features in the SDL_OS2_JOYSTICK environment variable in a batch file or CONFIG.SYS, so SDL applications can provide full capability to your device. The syntax is:</para>
<para>SET SDL_OS2_JOYSTICK=[JOYSTICK_NAME] [AXES] [BUTTONS] [HATS] [BALLS]</para>
<para>So, it you have a Gravis GamePad with 4 axes, 2 buttons, 2 hats and 0 balls, the line should be:</para>
<para>SET SDL_OS2_JOYSTICK=Gravis_GamePad 4 2 2 0</para>
<para>If you want to add spaces in your joystick name, just surround it with quotes or double-quotes:</para>
<para>SET SDL_OS2_JOYSTICK=&apos;Gravis GamePad&apos; 4 2 2 0</para>
<para>or</para>
<para>SET SDL_OS2_JOYSTICK=&quot;Gravis GamePad&quot; 4 2 2 0</para>
<para>Note however that Balls and Hats are not supported under OS/2, and the value will be ignored... but it is wise to define these correctly because in the future those can be supported.</para>
<para>Also the number of buttons is limited to 2 when using two joysticks, 4 when using one joystick with 4 axes, 6 when using a joystick with 3 axes and 8 when using a joystick with 2 axes. Notice however these are limitations of the Joystick Port hardware, not OS/2. </para>
</sect1>
    </detaileddescription>
    <location file="D:/RayTracing/docs/README-os2.md"/>
  </compounddef>
</doxygen>
